A Guide to the Papers of Louis I. Jaffé, 1920-1949
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Louis I. Jaffé 1920-1949
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9924-g
Ca. 900 items (2 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition to the Jaffé collection was presented to the Library by Mrs. Louis I. Jaffé of Norfolk, Virginia on April 29, 1980.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis I. Jaffé was born in Detroit, Michigan, February 22, 1888, the son of Phillip and Lotta Maria (Kahn) Jaffé. When Jaffé was twelve years old, his family moved to Durham, North Carolina, and he graduated from high school there in 1907. In 1911, he received an A.B. degree from Trinity College (now Duke University).
While a student at Trinity, Jaffé edited The Chronicle, a campus weekly, and was associate editor of The Archive, a college monthly. After graduation, he joined the staff of the Durham Sun, but left a short time later to become a reporter and assistant city editor for the Richmond Times- Dispatch.
In 1917, Jaffé was commissioned as Second Lieutenant in the Field Artillery Section, Officer's Reserve Corps of the United States Army. He was re-commissioned in the Aviation Section 1918, and again in 1919 with the Service of Supply. He was honorably discharged in France, March 29, 1919, and was commissioned as Inspector in the American National Red Cross with rank of Captain. He served on the Red Cross Commission to the Balkans from April to July, 1919, and was director of the Red Cross News Service in Paris from July to October, 1919. He was made a Chevalier of the State of Roumania, and honor bestowed in recognition of his work there with the Red Cross Commission.
After the war, Jaffé went to Norfolk to become editor of the Virginian-Pilot, a position he held from 1919 until his death in 1950. He was prominent among Virginia liberal journalists and won the Pulitzer Prize in 1929 for an editorial deploring a lynching which took place in Houston, Texas, on the eve of the Democratic National Convention.
In one of his last editorials, dated February 25, 1950, concerning the "mercy killing" of the Boothe bill for desegregation of Virginia public transportation he wrote: "The Virginia Democratic organization makes haste slowly in the field of social-political reform...It is still too uneasy about the impact of de-segregation on common carries to give the proposal anything like an official blessing. That will come later-after a longer look at this highly desirable reform, and possibly after another shove or two from the Supreme Court of the United States."
Scope and Content
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé Papers, 1920-1949, consists of ca. 900 items (2 boxes), chiefly Jaffé's alphabetical correspondence files "O" through "R." The correspondents include Virginia governors John Garland Pollard, George C. Peery, James H. Price, and U.S. Senator A. Willis Robertson. Other correspondents include newspaper and magazine editors and writers; state and national government officials; local merchants, businessmen, lawyers, officials, and clergy; and authors. An item-by-item annotated listing of the correspondence was prepared by Mrs. Jaffé and is available upon request. Topics discussed in the correspondence include politics, literature, journalism, local development, state projects, and social issues.
The correspondence and newspaper clippings regarding Jaffé's Pulitzer Prize for the best editorial of 1929 consists of 316 items, and is the largest exchange in this section of his papers. It includes the official letter announcing the award, letters and telegrams of congratulation, a copy of the winning editorial, newspaper and magazine clippings of articles praising Jaffé, and other related items. Jaffé received letters of congratulation from Harry F. Byrd, Sr., French Strother, Edwin A. Alderman, Edwin Mims, and E. Griffith Dodgson, among others.
There is also an oversized certificate appointing Jaffé as a representative for Virginia at the Press Congress of the World in 1931.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically. Each letter "O" through "R" has one or two general folders followed by individual folders for the major correspondents. The material within the general folders is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and chronologically for each individual. The material within the individual folders follows a chronological arrangement. Two of the folders, "Poll Tax Newspaper Clippings," and "Pulitzer Prize Newspaper Clippings," do not contain any correspondence.
Contents List
- "O" General 1922-1944, 30 items (Box 1)
- Owens, Hamilton 1924-1947, 80 items (Box 1)
- Owens, John 1927-1947, 32 items (Box 1)
- "Pag" through "Pep" 1922-1949, 38 items (Box 2)
- "Per" through "Pul" 1920-1949, 44 items (Box 2)
- Patterson, Paul 1927-1941, 4 items (Box 2)
- Patton, Frances Gray (Mrs. Lewis Patton) 1947, 1949, 3 items (Box 2)
- Peery, George C. 1934-1937, 8 items (Box 2)
- Phelan, Hunter 1940-1947, 9 items (Box 2)
- Poetry Magazine 1927 Jan 25, 1 item (Box 2)
- Polk, William T. 1944, 6 items (Box 2)
- Poll Tax Study 1945, 1946, 2 items (Box 2)
- Poll Tax Newspaper Clippings 1936, 12 items (Box 2)
- Pollard, John Garland 1923-1936, 35 items (Box 2)
- Pomfret, John E. 1948, 2 items (Box 2)
- Pope, Abner 1931-1942, 13 items (Box 2)
- Potts, Major Allen 1920-1926, 13 items (Box 2)
- Powell, John 1931, 2 items (Box 2)
- Pretlow, Mary Denson 1921-1933, 1946, 7 items (Box 2)
- Price, James H. 1938-1941, 6 items (Box 2)
- Prieur, William L., Jr. 1933-1943, 4 items (Box 2)
- Pulitzer Prize, announcement and correspodence pertaining to bestowal 1929, 4 items (Box 2)
- Pulitzer Prize article and editorial clippings 1929, 12 items (Box 2)
- Pulitzer Prize, congratulations and request for the winning editorial w/replies 1929 May-June, 2 folders; 256 items (Box 2)
- Pulitzer Prize, letters re compilations of editorial 1941-1943, 4 items (Box 2)
- Pulitzer Prize, newspaper clippings of articles and editorials re the award 1929-1930, 36 items (Box 2)
- "Rac" through "Ric" 1920-1949, 58 items (Box 3)
- "Rie" through "Rya" 1921-1945, 84 items (Box 3)
- Reid, Fergus 1921-1939, 9 items (Box 3)
- Reynolds, L.R. 1929-1933, 6 items (Box 3)
- Roads and Railroads 1929-1930, 7 items (Box 3)
- Robertson, Willis A. 1947-1949, 14 items (Box 3)
- Robertson, William J. 1922-1934, 18 items (Box 2)
- Rosenbaum, Edwin J. 1929, 6 items (Box 3)
- Certificate appointing Jaffé as a representative for Virginia at the Press Congress of the World 1931, 1 item
- Framed photograph of Allen Potts n.d., 1 item